<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-23T15:01:34+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Elucidata - Your AI experience</title><subtitle>Elucidata - AI Starter kits Experience. AI Starter Kits with complementary video tutorials, Interactive Experience, Bring Your Own Data workshops.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Novel approach on contextual anomaly detection presented at IEEE International Conference on Evolving and Adaptive Systems 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/conscious-ieee24-paper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Novel approach on contextual anomaly detection presented at IEEE International Conference on Evolving and Adaptive Systems 2024" /><published>2024-07-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-07-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/conscious_ieee24_paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/conscious-ieee24-paper"><![CDATA[<!-- <div class="text-md text-gray-700 "> -->

<p>Ensuring the smooth operation of industrial assets is more important than ever. Effective condition monitoring is crucial for maintaining optimal performance and avoiding costly downtime. However, condition monitoring of assets operating in highly dynamic environments (which is an inherent characteristic of many industrial processes) remains a challenge. How do you stay ahead of the curve when dealing with dynamic operating conditions of industrial processes?</p>

<p>At the 2024 IEEE International Conference on Evolving and Adaptive Intelligent Systems (IEEE EAIS 2024) in Madrid, we presented a novel method for raising alarms if performance deviations are detected while taking the dynamic operating conditions into account. Raising alarms about performance deviations helps operators to identify problems early. We showed that our method is performant and explainable.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="Method" src="src/assets/conscious_ieee24_paper2.webp" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The proposed methodology for anomaly detection takes varying operating contexts into account by extending the multi-view approach introduced in
<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10194172" target="_blank" alt="Multi-view contextual performance profiling in rotating machinery" class="text-blue-600 underline">our previous paper</a>. During the “offline phase”, the asset’s operating modes are estimated using a separate set of parameters. These parameters, which profile the underlying process, form the “process view”. For instance, typical parameters indicative of the operating mode in a pump include the rotational speed and the water pressure. Grouping similar parameter configurations in the same operating mode enables taking changes of operating conditions into account. Additionally, a separate view profiles the asset’s vibration behavior. Vibrations are indicative of the asset’s performance. Hence, we refer to this view as “performance view”. By combining the results of both views, a comprehensive picture of the asset’s behavior under different operating conditions is constructed by means of context-specific vibration fingerprints.</p>

<p>During the “online phase”, our method continuously compares the observed vibrations with the vibration fingerprints. If they differ significantly, an alarm is sent out automatically to the operator indicating an anomaly. Since the underlying process is monitored separately in the process view, changes in observed vibrations caused by a change in the operating context will not trigger an alarm. At the same time, our approach tracks potential changes in the underlying operating context to prevent false alarms due to previously unseen operating conditions.</p>

<p>We demonstrated the applicability of our approach on real-world industrial data of feedwater pumps provided by our partners I-Care and Engie. Furthermore, we proved that our method could achieve a high performance on a publicly available datasets with gearboxes.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="Presentation at conference " src="src/assets/conscious_ieee24_paper3.webp" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Interested in further details? The peer-reviewed publication “Unsupervised context-sensitive anomaly detection on streaming data relying on multi-view profiling” is available in <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10569106" target="_blank" alt="Unsupervised context-sensitive anomaly detection on streaming data relying on multi-view profiling" class="text-blue-600 underline">the proceedings of IEEE EAIS 2024 on IEEE Xplore</a>. This research was funded by the Flemish Government (AI Research Program) and by Flanders Innovation &amp; Entrepreneurship (VLAIO) via the CONSCIOUS project (HBC.2020.2795).</p>

<!-- </div> -->]]></content><author><name>Fabian Fingerhut</name></author><category term="Awards" /><category term="Projects" /><category term="Papers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ensuring the smooth operation of industrial assets is more important than ever. Effective condition monitoring is crucial for maintaining optimal performance and avoiding costly downtime. However, condition monitoring of assets operating in highly dynamic environments (which is an inherent characteristic of many industrial processes) remains a challenge. How do you stay ahead of the curve when dealing with dynamic operating conditions of industrial processes?.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/conscious_ieee24_paper.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/conscious_ieee24_paper.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Collaboration with Materialise and Cr3do selected for the ITEA Award of Excellence for Innovation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/samuel-itea-excellence-award" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collaboration with Materialise and Cr3do selected for the ITEA Award of Excellence for Innovation" /><published>2023-06-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/SAMUEL_ITEA_Excellence_Award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/samuel-itea-excellence-award"><![CDATA[<div class="text-md text-gray-700 ">


Joint collaboration with Materialise and Cr3do selected for the ITEA Award of Excellence 2023 for Innovation

 Although the additive manufacturing (AM) technology has evolved substantially over the last decades, the overall end to-end process involves many complex steps and still today requires manual input from an engineer at crucial points. We have been collaborating with Materialise and Cr3do to create an AM knowledge base that can assist in all major AM steps. The success of this collaboration has led to the project being selected for the ITEA Award of Excellence 2023 for Innovation

Materialise is the largest company active in 3D-printing world-wide. It was founded in 1990 in Leuven, Belgium and has grown to a company with more than 2.100 employees world-wide, with strong international presence in software, industrial and medical applications with AM. Materialise has the largest group of software developers for AM and with more than 250 high-end industrial printers, is the largest service provider of AM parts in Europe.
Cr3do is an SME specializing in generating personalized solutions for customers by using modern, smart manufacturing techniques such as AM and laser cutting, to lower the threshold for other SMEs to get started with these technologies. The company provides expertise, 3D modeling services and production of their solutions. Most customers are active in the architectural and residential development sector, for which Cr3do creates high-end 3D models and 3D visuals.
Although the AM technology has evolved substantially over the last decades, the overall end-to-end process involves many complex steps that still today requires manual input from an engineer at crucial points. We have been collaborating with Materialise and Cr3do in the context of the ITEA3-SAMUEL project to combine an AM engineer’s experience with data-driven machine-learning methods to create an AM knowledge base that can assist in all major AM steps. The focus of the Belgian partners is on use cases related to build-time estimation (BTE) and build preparation (e.g. part orientation and nesting).

Data-driven build-time estimation
Accurate estimation of build times of 3D objects is of great importance in the different phases of an AM process including: 1) during quotation, an estimation of build time is needed since it impacts the printing cost of a part significantly, 2) during build preparation, part orientation influences build time significantly, hence information on build time can be exploited to find the optimal part orientation and, 3) at planning level, information on build time allows for optimal planning, maximizing machine utilization and minimizing total production time.
The existing physics-based models can very precisely tackle this task but at the cost of spending a considerable amount of time. An alternative solution is to use a data-driven machine learning method for BTE. However, estimating build times of a dataset of objects with diverse and heterogeneous characteristics is a challenging task for a single learning algorithm.

<br />
<center><img alt="Method" src="src/assets/samuel_itea_award2.png" class="center" /><figcaption>(left) Examples of the modeled 3D objects with diverse characteristics, (right) complex and non-linear relations between the objects’ volumes and their build times</figcaption></center>
<br />

We therefore investigated the value of the ‘divide-and-conquer’ strategy in partitioning the dataset into subsets of homogeneous objects to facilitate the BTE task for the examined learning models. The usefulness of this strategy has been proven through performing comprehensive experiments. We proposed two different divide-and-conquer algorithms and the experimental results showed that both methods are indeed capable of providing accurate BTEs and can outperform the performance of a single learning method trained with all objects in the dataset. More specifically, the proposed algorithms yielded a mean relative estimation error below 10% for all objects and below 5% for around 40% of the objects in the dataset.

The proposed data-driven divide-and-conquer strategies and the obtained results were published in <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/conhome/9679833/proceeding" target="_blank" class="text-blue-600 underline">2021 International Conference on Data Mining Workshops (ICDMW) (DOI: 10.1109/ICDMW53433.2021.00041).</a>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Robbert Verbeke</name></author><category term="Awards" /><category term="Projects" /><category term="Papers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have been collaborating with Materialise and Cr3do to create an AM knowledge base that can assist in all major AM steps. The success of this collaboration has led to the project being selected for the **ITEA Award of Excellence 2023 for Innovation**.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/samuel_itea_award1_piqsels.com-id-zmdsp.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/samuel_itea_award1_piqsels.com-id-zmdsp.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our team won the Best Industry Paper Award at the IEEE Conference on Prognostics and Health Management</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/conscious-phmc-award" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our team won the Best Industry Paper Award at the IEEE Conference on Prognostics and Health Management" /><published>2023-06-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CONSCIOUS_PHMC_Award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/conscious-phmc-award"><![CDATA[<h3 id="a-team-of-researchers-from-our-elucidata-lab-wins-best-industry-paper-award-at-ieee-conference-on-prognostics-and-health-management-montreal-québec-june-5---june-7-2023">A team of researchers from our EluciDATA Lab wins Best Industry Paper Award at IEEE Conference on Prognostics and Health Management (Montreal, Québec, June 5 - June 7, 2023)</h3>
<p><br />
Investigating the performance of industrial assets poses a challenge due to the complex dynamic operating environment that machines typically are exposed to under in real-world conditions. In order to avoid unplanned and expensive downtime it is crucial to properly assess the asset’s health status. Our award-winning paper, titled <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10194172" target="_blank" alt="Multi-view Contextual Performance Profiling in Rotating Machinery" class="text-blue-600 underline">“Multi-view Contextual Performance Profiling in Rotating Machinery”</a>. addresses this challenge by introducing an innovative unsupervised approach. As part of AI-ICON CONSCIOUS project, and in collaboration with <b>I-Care</b> and <b>Engie</b>, our research confronts the task of accurately estimating an asset’s performance by considering the varying contexts to which industrial assets are exposed during operation. Our work emphasizes the importance of understanding the factors that shape these contexts and account for them during asset condition monitoring and profiling. We validated the approach on a real-world dataset of feedwater pumps, demonstrating its tangible applicability to industrial problems. In this article we will sketch how our insightful approach can enhance asset management strategies.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="Multi-view representation for performance profiling" src="src/assets/conscious_phmc_award2b.png" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The proposed methodology leverages a <b>multi-view representation</b> and matrix decomposition to derive specific vibration fingerprints characterizing the asset’s behavior in a context-sensitive fashion. The approach processes data in two separate views: the process view and the vibration view.&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>In the <b>process view</b>, variables related to the asset’s internal workings are analyzed and partitioned, with each measurement point associated with a specific label representing the operating modes of the asset.
On the other hand, the <b>vibration view</b> focuses on extracting vibration profiles through non-negative matrix decomposition. By linking these two views together, the researchers can derive characteristic fingerprints using a suitable contextual representation and performance-related indicators.
This methodology was validated using real-world industrial data from feedwater pumps, comprising vibration and operational sensor measurements. The results obtained from the validation demonstrate the efficacy of the profiling methodology in delivering meaningful risk assessment estimations associated with different operating contexts. At the 2023 IEEE Conference on Prognostics and Health Management our paper was awarded with the Best Industry Paper Award recognizing the continuous effort we put in our day-to-day work at the EluciDATA Lab to bridge the gap between AI research and practical applications for the industry.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The results obtained from the validation demonstrate the efficacy of the profiling methodology in delivering meaningful risk assessment estimations associated with different operating contexts.
This award can be seen as an affirmation of our day-to-day work at the EluciDATA Lab to bridge the gap between AI research and practical applications for the industry.</p>]]></content><author><name>Fabian Fingerhut</name></author><category term="Projects" /><category term="Awards" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our award-winning paper, titled "Multi-view Contextual Performance Profiling in Rotating Machinery," introduces an innovative unsupervised approach for asset performance profiling. The proposed methodology addresses the challenge of accurately estimating an asset's performance by considering the varying contexts to which industrial assets are exposed during operation.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/conscious_phmc_award1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/conscious_phmc_award1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sir Adas’ series The invisible war against women</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-invisible-war-against-women" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sir Adas’ series The invisible war against women" /><published>2022-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the_invisible_war_against_women</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-invisible-war-against-women"><![CDATA[<p>We have not done a lot of SirAdas blogging recently. The workload has taken the upper hand in our daily lives and then there was the insane war in Ukraine. History repeating again … few machos showing off with power and weapons. And as always, the victims are mostly women and children. However, there is another war which has been ongoing for centuries, namely the invisible violence against women. Occasionally we get reminded of it, either via some horrible news in the media or being confronted with it in our own lives. This time it was a regular post from Katrien Van Geystelen, the best voice coach I ever had. Typically, her posts are very cheerful, full of interesting insights and useful tips about how to best use your voice. Not this one! You can read the <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6929768751680643072/" target="_blank" class="text-blue-600 underline">original post in Dutch here</a>
For those of you not speaking Dutch, here a very short summary of Katrien’s post. She described how after attending a very inspirational evening event (as she brilliantly puts it, an event with very high “we can” content) for entrepreneurs, she and another female participant had to run scared through an underground parking being chased by 3 young men. Luckily, they managed to reach safely their cars on time.
Katrien’s story is so recognisable. I’m sure almost every woman has experienced something similar at least once in her life. I had to think about the last time I experienced something like this, about 4-5 years ago. I was at an offsite with my team somewhere in Limburg. In the late afternoon of the second day, my teammates were busy with some team building activities in the gardens of the domain where we were staying.</p>

<p><br />
 I decided to go running. It was a warm summer day and I headed towards the forest bordering the domain dressed in jogging shorts. I was just entering the forest when I heard behind me the irritating noise of a motorcycle, which obviously had some problems with its exhaust. Very characteristic! The motorcycle overtook me and the guy driving it gave me some strange feeling. While passing me he turned his head back several times to look at me. A woman knows when it doesn’t feel right!</p>

<p><br />
I continued running for several minutes somewhat alert and anxious. We had a walk in the forest the evening before when we arrived. Thus I knew that the black road through it was about a kilometre long and completely surrounded by very densely grown tall trees. So once inside the forest, nobody outside could see nor hear you anymore.
All of a sudden I realised that something changed. What? I didn’t hear anymore the irritating noise of badly working motorcycle exhaust. I thought this was strange. He didn’t seem to drive very fast to so quickly disappear, but I could not see far enough since the road was turning. I took the turn and there some 200 meters ahead I could see the guy with the motorcycle standing still (waiting for me?) and looking towards me.
<br />
 It felt immediately as I needed to make the most important decision of my life. I had to admit that only for some very tiny split second I contemplated to just carry on with running. Then I just turned back sprinting faster and faster as I was hearing somewhere behind me the noise of badly working exhaust approaching …
In despair, not being able to further increase my pace from exhaustion, I approached the end of the forest seeing through the trees my teammates far away fully occupied with their activities, without any awareness of my struggle. I started jumping (to be seen above the fence) and shouting as crazy. First they ignored me thinking I am just being funny, but at the end one of them run towards me from the other side of the fence. I was safe! At that moment the motorcycle passed next to me, and the guy turned back his head examining carefully my scarcely dressed in jogging shorts body …
There I was, a successful professional woman, mature and assertive, leading a team of talented people often looking up to me for advice and support, transferred into a humiliated and scared child. Mother of 2 children, but not being able to even have a short running session in the countryside on my own. We had a team dinner that evening. I was still shaken by the afternoon incident, but when I tried to share my state of mind with my, predominantly male, teammates I was shocked by their indifference and disinterest.
<br />
 They wanted just to have fun, teasing and sharing jokes with each other. I felt as a paranoid female, overdramatising the facts. I started doubting myself, maybe it was not really dangerous. I just over-exaggerated it, I imagined it, …. Did I? No, I didn’t! I was really very lucky! However, many women have been and will be much less lucky as described by Rebecca Solnit in her essay <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Men_Explain_Things_to_Me" target="_blank" class="text-blue-600 underline"><em>The longest war</em></a>.</p>

<p><br />
I do not actually know how to finish my blog. I shared my story with Katrien in response to her post. This is what she wrote back to me: “Yesterday my colleague and I went to the police office to report what happened. To be honest I can write a new story about that… We were not stimulated to report it at all. It’s a shame!”</p>

<p><br />
It is indeed a shame!  The end of the longest war, as Rebecca Solnit defined it, is unfortunately not yet in sight …</p>]]></content><author><name>Elena Tsiporkova</name></author><category term="Sir_Adas&apos;_series" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have not done a lot of SirAdas blogging recently. The workload has taken the upper hand in our daily lives and then there was the insane war in Ukraine. History repeating again … few machos showing off with power and weapons. And as always, the victims are mostly women and children. However, there is another war which has been ongoing for centuries, namely the invisible violence against women.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_invisible_war.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_invisible_war.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Giving circular economy a boost by improving refurbishment process of household appliances</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/giving-circular-economy-a-boost" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giving circular economy a boost by improving refurbishment process of household appliances" /><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/giving_circular_economy_a_boost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/giving-circular-economy-a-boost"><![CDATA[<p><br />
A small part of discarded household appliances that are now shredded could be reused or refurbished, or their components reused in the refurbishing process. Refurnished household appliances can offer people in energy poverty an alternative to energy-consuming appliances. Through advanced data analytics and cognitive and assistive operator support the efficiency of the refurbishing process can be increased.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>97% of the household appliances are shredded after return or recycled as raw material. In most cases these devices are relatively recent, and up to 10% can be reused or refurbished in an ecologically and economically responsible manner. Moreover, between 15% and 30% of these machines contain functioning components that can be resold as spare parts or reused in the refurbishing process. Providing more refurnished appliances helps families in energy poverty to replace energy-consuming household appliances.<em> </em></p>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="brefurbish-increasing-efficiency-of-refurbishing-process">BrefurbiSH: Increasing efficiency of refurbishing process</h3>

<p><br /></p>

<p>With the support of Innoviris, Sirris, Circular.Brussels and BSH started in 2021 the BrefurbiSH project for increasing the efficiency of the refurbishing process of household appliances through advanced data analytics and cognitive and assistive operator support.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The refurbishing sector is still a very manual labour-intensive sector where target group employees perform a very repetitive sequence of instructions or tasks. In the BrefubiSH project we would increase the efficiency of household refurbishment by providing extra support to the employees. We will gather appliance-specific data before, during and after the refurbishment to extract insights on which appliances are more prone to faults and what type of error is most common. These insights can be fed back to the design process of the same type of appliances as such that design choices can be made to facilitate the refurbishing of household appliances in the future.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Data extracted during the refurbishment can be used to automatically build a refurbishing guideline that is needed to train new target group employees. The traditional refurbishing infrastructure will be enhanced using advanced data analytics and cognitive and assistive operator support. The efficiency will be validated through a pilot infrastructure installed at Circular.Brussels targeting two representative appliances of the BSH appliances, namely washing machines and dishwashers.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="BrefurbiSH_0.png" src="src/assets/BrefurbiSH_0.png" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p><em>Project subsidized by the Brussels-Capital Region - Innoviris.</em><br />
<br /></p>
<center><img alt="RGB_innoviris_we fund your future_MAIN LOGO.jpg" src="src/assets/RGB_innoviris_we fund your future_MAIN LOGO.jpg" class="center" href="https://innoviris.brussels/" target="_blank" /></center>
<p><br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Kevin Van Vaerenbergh</name></author><category term="Circular economy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A small part of discarded household appliances that are now shredded could be reused or refurbished, or their components reused in the refurbishing process. Refurnished household appliances can offer people in energy poverty an alternative to energy-consuming appliances. Through advanced data analytics and cognitive and assistive operator support the efficiency of the refurbishing process can be increased.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/Brefurbish_washer.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/Brefurbish_washer.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Today, as a Woman, You Can Do Anything, But You Must Not Do Anything!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/today-as-a-woman-you-can-do-anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Today, as a Woman, You Can Do Anything, But You Must Not Do Anything!" /><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/today_as_a_woman_you_can_do_anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/today-as-a-woman-you-can-do-anything"><![CDATA[<p>June 16th, 1963: Vostok 6, with Valentina (Valia) Tereshkova on board, was launched in space. The first, the youngest (only 26) and the only woman who has ever flown in space on a solo mission. Whau!</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>At that time, me and my identical twin sister were still in the belly of my mother, fighting who will be the first one out to discover the world …. Well, in case you are curious, I kicked her out on an exploration mission.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Tereshkova volunteered in 1961 for the cosmonaut program and was accepted although she had no pilot training. However, she was already an accomplished amateur parachutist. Her Vostok 6 mission lasted just under three days (two days, 23 hours, and 12 minutes). With a single flight, she had logged more flight time than all the US Mercury astronauts who had flown to that date combined. [1,3]</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Nevertheless, it cannot be that a woman achieves greatness without the world doubting the genuineness of her achievements. Tereshkova’s flight was for a long time surrounded with some mystery e.g., insinuations that she had been too ill to conduct the planned tests and even hinting that she had challenged orders. There is no evidence suggesting that she was more ill than anybody else (a man) could be expected to be in the given circumstances. She maintained a flight log and performed various tests to collect data on her body’s reaction to spaceflight. Her photographs of Earth and the horizon were later used to identify aerosol layers within the atmosphere. [2]</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>However, she did challenge orders and she had a very good reason to do so. She discovered very soon after lift-off that the settings for re-entry were incorrect, to the point where she would have sped into outer space, rather than back to Earth. She was eventually sent new settings but had to keep this a secret for 30 years, until the man who made the mistake was dead. [2]</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Some months ago, I came across an interesting article mentioning Tereshkova to support the claim that Soviet Russia had a better record of training women in STEM than America does today. The article (based on Roshanna Sylvester contribution at the Russian History Blog) is citing a letter from a girl from Ukraine to Yuri Gagarin. Inspired by Tereshkova’s flight, the girl is confident that even she (as she puts it “a simple village girl”) will be able to fly to the cosmos if receiving the same training as Valia Tereshkova did from Gagarin. In contrast to this, in a letter to John Glenn, an American girl wrote that she would very much like to become an astronaut, but since she is a 15-year-old girl, she fears it would be impossible.[4]</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>When reading this, I had to think about something Fintje Moerman (Flemish Minister of Economy, Innovation, and Science 2004-2007) said some years ago in a magazine interview: “If I were a man, I would live in a society that was written to my size. Men still set the standard. As a result, they also must face greater social pressure. Today, as a woman, you can do anything, but you must not do anything. The disadvantage is that you must find the drive in yourself. I sometimes miss that in young women. Legally, there is no longer any obstacle and yet they do not seize all opportunities” (free translation from Dutch). [5]</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Growing up in the Communist Eastern Europe, I never understood why women here in the Democratic West are often putting limits to themselves and their own professional choices. Women have been for too long pictured and praised only as the perfect mothers and household wives. I guess it was just very convenient (and economically beneficial) to let women do most of the unpaid household work and children and parents’ care. I doubt it really proved very beneficial in the long term to lose the talents of 50% of the population.</p>

<p>It is not that there was no sexism in the Communist Eastern Europe at the time. My mother still did most of the cooking and cleaning, while my father was reading the newspaper. There was of course quite some “mansplaining” too [6]. However, all the mothers were working. My mother could travel for meetings and conferences abroad, while my father was taking care of us. In fact, I did not know anybody whose mother did not work. I never felt that, as a woman, I was limited in my study and career choices and certainly, I did not feel that “hard sciences” and technology are not for me but only for men. My father encouraged me and my sister to study mathematics since he believed this would open many doors for us professionally. It did, indeed!</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Tereshkova’s father was a tractor driver and her mother worked in a textile factory. Interested in parachuting from a young age, Tereshkova began skydiving at a local flying club, making her first jump at the age of 22 in May 1959. At the time of her selection as a cosmonaut, she was working as a textile worker in a local factory [1], but this did not stop her to pursue her dream! And it did not stop her to be a mother either!</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><br />
<a href="http://www.esa.int/About_Us/ESA_history/50_years_of_humans_in_space/First_woman_in_space_Valentina" target="_blank" alt="ESA - First woman in space - Valentina Tereshkova" class="text-blue-600 underline">ESA - First woman in space - Valentina Tereshkova</a> ([1])</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2017/mar/29/valentina-tereshkova-first-woman-in-space-people-waste-money-on-wars" target="_blank" alt="Valentina Tereshkova: 'People waste money on wars" class="text-blue-600 underline">Valentina Tereshkova: ‘People waste money on wars</a> ([2])</p>

<p><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Valentina-Tereshkova" target="_blank" alt="Valentina Tereshkova" class="text-blue-600 underline">Valentina Tereshkova</a> ([3])</p>

<p><a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/soviet-russia-had-a-better-record-of-training-women-in-stem-than-america-does-today-180948141/" target="_blank" alt="Soviet Russia Had a Better Record of Training Women in STEM Than America Does Today" class="text-blue-600 underline">Soviet Russia Had a Better Record of Training Women in STEM Than America Does Today</a> ([4])</p>

<p><a href="https://www.knack.be/nieuws/wereld/wat-als-ik-een-man-was-geweest/article-normal-89077.html" target="_blank" alt="Wat als ik een man was geweest?" class="text-blue-600 underline">Wat als ik een man was geweest?</a> ([5])</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mansplaining" target="_blank" alt="Mansplaining" class="text-blue-600 underline">Mansplaining</a> ([6])</p>]]></content><author><name>Elena Tsiporkova</name></author><category term="Sir_Adas&apos;_series" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[June 16th, 1963; Vostok 6, with Valentina (Valia) Tereshkova on board, was launched in space. The first, the youngest (only 26) and the only woman who has ever flown in space on a solo mission. Whau!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_you_can_do_anything.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_you_can_do_anything.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sir Adas’ series; Women cannot play chess!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/women-cannot-play-chess" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sir Adas’ series; Women cannot play chess!" /><published>2021-06-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/women_cannot_play_chess</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/women-cannot-play-chess"><![CDATA[<p>It is Corona times and there is not much to do in the evenings. Thus, we bought a Netflix subscription some months ago and The Queen’s Gambit was one of the first things we enjoyed. The celebrated drama series is telling the story of the genius female chess player, wining all games against men - not many women in the game in the 1960s.  Of course, she could only do this thanks to her drug and alcohol dependency. No woman can beat a man in an intellectual game without some help from outside, right!</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Around the same time, an article[1] appeared in the Knack magazine about Judit Polgár, the best female chess player of all times. On a Sunday afternoon, I was reading with admiration about</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>how she and her 2 sisters enjoyed the same spartan upbringing of their father, who she defeated in chess for the first time at the age of five,
how at the age of fifteen years and five months old, she became the youngest Grandmaster of all time, knocking the legendary Bobby Fischer off the throne
how the reigning world champion at the time Garry Kasparov, openly shared his conviction that women would never reach the highest level due to “the imperfections of the female psyche”
how in 2002’s tournament “Russia vs The Rest of the World”, Judit Polgár finally defeated Garry Kasparov, despite the so-called imperfections of the female psyche
and how other world champions shared his fate, amongst them Magnus Carlsen, Viswanathan Anand, and Anatoli Karpov.
However, my admiration transformed into indignation when I reached a passage talking about the Dutch grandmaster Johannes Donner. He wrote in 1968 a piece on women and chess in the women’s magazine Avenue, concluding “However painful it may be, we must not hesitate to face the truth: Women cannot play chess.”</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Feeling really upset, I recited this piece of text to my Dutch husband. He demonstrated adequate empathy by exclaiming “But, this was such a long time ago!”</p>

<p>REALLY? Even the sweetest man does not have a clue how it feels to go through life as a woman!</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>I recalled an evening on one of our skis vacations some 3-4 years ago. My husband was playing chess with my son and was mercifully defeating him game after game - father instinct obviously does not have a chance against the eagerness to win. The situation was getting dramatic, not being able to bare any further the frustration of my child, my mother instinct made me suggest I play a match with my husband instead.</p>

<p>In less than 15 minutes, I defeated him. He completely underestimated me. What he didn’t know was that my sister and I also enjoyed very spartan upbringing and played often chess with my father, who was good at it. So, my husband was sitting there embarrassed, full of disbelief and wanted to immediately rematch. Well, my victory, reflected in the admiring eyes of my son, tasted so sweet! - “No thank you, I am going to bed!”</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Never played chess again with my husband … and now I know what to say next time this topic comes up in our family discussions: “However painful it may be, we must not hesitate to face the truth: Bulgarian women are much better in chess than Dutch men!”</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>[1] <a href="https://www.knack.be/nieuws/geschiedenis/judit-polgar-de-beste-schaakster-aller-tijden-ze-eet-je-met-huid-en-haar-op-als-een-lieflijk-monster/article-longread-1684359.html" target="_blank" alt="Judit Polgar" class="text-blue-600 underline">Judit Polgar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Elena Tsiporkova</name></author><category term="Sir_Adas&apos;_series" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is Corona times and there is not much to do in the evenings. Thus, we bought a Netflix subscription some months ago and The Queen’s Gambit was one of the first things we enjoyed. The celebrated drama series is telling the story of the genius female chess player, wining all games against men - not many women in the game in the 1960s. Of course, she could only do this thanks to her drug and alcohol dependency. No woman can beat a man in an intellectual game without some help from outside, right!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_women_cannot_play_chess.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/sir_adas_women_cannot_play_chess.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sir Adas’ series; Ada Lovelace, the first programmer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ada-lovelace-the-first-programmer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sir Adas’ series; Ada Lovelace, the first programmer" /><published>2021-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ada_lovelace_the_first_programmer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ada-lovelace-the-first-programmer"><![CDATA[<p>Programming is for men! With roughly <a href="https://werk.belgie.be/nl/publicaties/de-loonkloof-tussen-vrouwen-en-mannen-belgie-rapport-2021" target="_blank" alt="Gender gap salary" class="text-blue-600 underline">23 %[1] female workers in the IT sector in Belgium</a>, this assumption seems to suggest itself. And still, the first person ever regarded to be a programmer was a woman – namely Ada Lovelace back in 1843.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Supported by her mother – in her opinion to prevent her from developing her father’s (Lord Byron) perceived insanity – she eagerly studied mathematics and logic. When meeting Charles Babbage and learning about his Analytical Engine she was enthusiastic about the idea of a machine that</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p><em>“has no pretensions whatever to originate anything. It can do whatever we know how to order it to perform. It can follow analysis; but it has no power of anticipating any analytical relations or truths.”</em></p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Not only that she developed a method for calculating the Bernoulli number on the Analytical Engine (considered the first published algorithm ever, but unfortunately never built), it was her driving the work and believing in it. That given, she was not only a talented mathematician but also a visioner and innovation driver. And most importantly, recognized as such by others (amongst them many men) in a time and age when women were still seen as just a pretty adornment of the décor.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>On the international day of women in mathematics, we are happy to announce the birth of a new blog series, namely the SirAdas blog. Its mission is to spread and promote achievements of women passionate about science, technology and innovation. In other words, the modern Ada Lovelaces.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Let’s celebrate and cherish women’s intelligence and creativity! Follow and contribute to our blog!</p>]]></content><author><name>Sarah Klein</name></author><category term="Sir_Adas&apos;_series" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Programming is for men! Withroughly 23 %1female workers in the IT sector in Belgium, this assumption seems to suggest itself. And still, the first person ever regarded to be a programmer was a woman namelyAda Lovelaceback in 1843.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/ada-lovelace-1068x653-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/ada-lovelace-1068x653-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is traffic volume correlated to Covid-19 infections?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/is-traffic-volume-correlated-to" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is traffic volume correlated to Covid-19 infections?" /><published>2021-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/is_traffic_volume_correlated_to</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/is-traffic-volume-correlated-to"><![CDATA[<p>This is the fifth blog in a series of blogs concerning the traffic situation in Brussels in times of Covid-19 restrictions. This work has been realized in the context of the <em>MISTic</em> project, executed by the EluciDATA Lab with with <a href="https://www.macq.eu/nl_BE/" target="_blank" alt="Macq" class="text-blue-600 underline">Macq</a> and <a href="https://www.vub.be/" target="_blank" alt="VUB" class="text-blue-600 underline">VUB</a> as partners.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Our previous analyses were based on a dataset of <a href="http://mobilite-mobiliteit.brussels/en" target="_blank" alt="Brussels Mobility" class="text-blue-600 underline">Brussels Mobility</a>, which contains vehicle counts from 55 busy locations in the city of Brussels. During the first lockdown in March 2020, we discovered, as communicated in our first blog ((<a href="insightful-blueprints-of-brussels-traffic" class="text-blue-600 underline">Insightful blueprints of Brussels traffic emerge in times of covid-19</a>)), that traffic had dramatically reduced overall, but less so on the small ring of Brussels, where peaks of up to 80% of retained traffic were observed. In the previous, 4th blog ((<a href="run-up-in-brussels-traffic-towards" class="text-blue-600 underline">Run-up in Brussels Traffic Towards the 2nd Covid-19 Peak</a>), we investigated the traffic volume evolution in relation to historical values since 2018, in order to consider the seasonality and holiday effects impacting traffic volumes. We observed that the traffic volumes in October 2020 were very close to normal (pre-Covid-19) conditions.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Today’s blog is inspired by a quote of virologist Steven Van Gucht in Het Journaal on December 9:</p>

<p><em>“…wat wel opvalt is dat we ons vaker verplaatsen… en daarvan weten we dat dat een vrij goede voorspelling is van het toekomstig aantal nieuwe besmettingen.”</em> <em>[… what is striking is that we move more often… and we know that that is a pretty good prediction of the future number of new infections.]</em>
<em>Steven Van Gucht</em></p>

<p>Since vehicle counts data is closely connected to people’s movements, it is worthwhile to investigate whether Steven Van Gucht’s statement is valid, i.e., how well traffic intensity correlates with, or even more predicts peaks in Covid-19 infections.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The blog reveals three main insights:</p>
<ol>
  <li>a certain threshold in traffic load needs to be exceeded in order to observe an effect on the number of Covid-19 related hospitalisations;</li>
  <li>there is a clear difference in effect on traffic between residential areas and more business strategic locations;</li>
  <li>peaks in Covid-19 hospitalisations follow peaks in traffic volumes with a very variable time offset depending on the time of the year.</li>
</ol>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="less-than-16-000-vehicles-a-day-in-brussels-controls-the-pandemic">Less than 16 000 vehicles a day in Brussels controls the pandemic</h2>

<p>As a first use case, we consider the average daily vehicle counts for 50 busy roads in the Brussels Capital Region since the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic in March 2020. In the figure below, the evolution of these vehicle counts is shown with a blue line. To smooth down the periodic drops due to weekend effects, a rolling window of the average per week is applied. The latter is also aligned with the way the Brussels Covid-19 hospitalisations are reported (orange line). Note that we use the number of new hospitalisations in this study, instead of the number of new infections. The hospitalisation rate also represents the presence of Covid-19, although it is typically lagging a bit behind the number of infections. The big advantage of this parameter is its stability since it is not affected by the varying testing strategy and capacity.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="Graphical user interface, chart, line chartDescription automatically generated" src="src/assets/Covid hospitalisations vs vehicle counts.png" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p><strong>Legend</strong>:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>DIY &amp; garden shops open</em></li>
  <li><em>B2B companies open</em></li>
  <li><em>B2C shops open</em></li>
  <li><em>Contact professions open</em></li>
  <li><em>Pubs &amp; restaurants closed</em></li>
  <li><em>Brussels: stricter curfew</em></li>
  <li><em>Non-essential shops can open again</em>
<br />
<br />
It is interesting to observe that a certain threshold in vehicle counts (around 16 000-17 000) had to be exceeded in order to provoke the reversal of increasing/decreasing trends in Covid-19 hospitalisations. The figure above shows clearly that during the first lockdown in 2020 traffic load decreased to nearly a third of its normal volume. A similar sudden drop in Covid-19 hospitalisations can be observed some weeks later in the beginning of April (mind the log scale). Remarkably, the Covid-19 hospitalisation numbers kept dropping until the beginning of July despite the clear gradual increase in vehicle counts. Subsequently, only in the end of June the vehicle counts clearly exceeded the threshold of 16 000 vehicles, finally resulting in a strong increase of Covid-19 hospitalisations in July. Similarly, the temporary fall in Covid-19 hospitalisations in the beginning of September can be explained by the valley below 16 000 in vehicle counts in the middle of the summer holidays. During the second lockdown, traffic counts were as well only temporary diving below the threshold, followed by a stagnation around the threshold value. As a result, the Covid-19 hospitalisations dropped only for a short period and even stagnated in the second half of December. Note that this threshold might deviate over time as it is depending on external factors as availability of mouth masks and people following the restrictions less stringently.</li>
</ol>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="increase-in-hospitalizations-in-flanders-is-also-preceded-by-more-traffic">Increase in hospitalizations in Flanders is also preceded by more traffic</h2>

<p>As an extension to the Brussels vehicle counts, we also consider vehicle counts from the <a href="https://www.telraam.net/en" class="text-blue-600 underline">Telraam</a> dataset. Telraam is an open project where citizens can monitor traffic by attaching a small camera to the inside of a window, which counts vehicles passing by. Since any citizen can participate, a large(r) number of locations can be monitored. Apart from the different Belgian regions, the big difference with the Brussels vehicle counts data is that the Telraam data is typically originating from residential areas, with hotspots in Leuven, Antwerp and Ghent. The Brussels vehicle counts originate from busier and critical traffic locations (e.g., the small ring). A drawback of the Telraam project is that such low-cost hardware is not able to detect vehicles after sunset. So, to allow for a fair comparison over all seasons, we excluded all counts before 9:00 and after 17:00. Additionally, locations with too few data points inside the time interval of interest (March 2020 – December 2020) were filtered out. Finally, we identified 379 qualitative vehicle counting locations in Flanders.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Based on this Telraam data, the same figure as in the Brussels case was constructed below. Focusing solely on the vehicle counts, one can observe a very similar traffic evolution up to the start of the second lockdown in November. However, in contrast to the Brussels numbers, a much steeper drop of vehicle counts was introduced in the beginning of November, leading to even less traffic than during the first lockdown. There can be different explanations for this phenomenon. Maybe Flanders is simply a better student than Brussels when it concerns following the Covid-19 restrictions and recommendations. Most probably, the difference could be attributed to the more residential character of the locations and the exclusion of the peak hours from the Telraam dataset. After all, this sudden drop does not seem to precede a very dramatic decrease in Covid-19 hospitalisations compared to the Brussels case. In general, one can observe again a very similar (lagging behind) behaviour of the vehicle counts and the Covid-19 hospitalisations.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<center><img alt="Graphical user interface, chart, line chartDescription automatically generated" src="src/assets/Covid hospitalisations vs vehicle counts 9 - 17.png" class="center" /></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="how-much-time-is-needed-to-see-the-effect-of-a-traffic-reduction">How much time is needed to see the effect of a traffic reduction?</h2>

<p>For both Brussels and Flanders, a delayed effect of the vehicle counts on the Covid-19 hospitalisations is observed. Although the window of delay between traffic and hospitalisation peaks seems very variable in the different periods, there is no doubt that there is some correlation between the vehicle counts evolution and the Covid-19 numbers.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>In order to support formally this statement, we calculated the Pearson correlation between the Covid-19 hospitalisations and the average vehicle counts for 3 so called “periods of interest”. Each period of interest represents a different stage (in terms of peaks) in the Covid-19 hospitalisations and is annotated in the two images above. Since we are interested in discovering which time offset leads to the highest correlation for each period of interest, the Pearson correlation was calculated for a time offset between 7 and 60 days for each period.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<ul>
  <li>The most optimal Pearson correlation during the <strong>first period of interest</strong> (the blue bar below the two plots) was obtained for both regions for a delay of 40-42 days. This indicates that the reduction in traffic (i.e., in people’s movement) needed 40-42 days before it took effect on the Covid-19 hospitalisations.</li>
  <li>For <strong>period of interest 2</strong> (small peak during summer break), the offset with the highest Pearson correlation was too high to be reliable. We suppose that too many different factors impacted the hospitalisation rate in the summer period, which obviously cannot be captured solely by traffic counts.</li>
  <li>In <strong>period of interest 3</strong> (the second major peak), the optimal Pearson correlation is obtained at a different offset in time for Brussels (36 days) and Flanders (22 days). Such a big difference in delay of effect can be attributed to the different nature of traffic data e.g., more business related in Brussels vs. residential in Flanders, more concentrated location counts in Brussels vs. fragmented ones in Flanders, etc. which are differently affected by Covid</li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>

<p><em>Project subsidized by the Brussels-Capital Region - Innoviris.</em><br />
<br /></p>
<center><img alt="RGB_innoviris_we fund your future_MAIN LOGO.jpg" src="src/assets/RGB_innoviris_we fund your future_MAIN LOGO.jpg" class="center" href="https://innoviris.brussels/" target="_blank" /></center>
<p><br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Michiel Dhont</name></author><category term="Intelligent_transportation_systems" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog is inspired by a quote of virologist Steven Van Gucht in Het Journaal on December 9; “... what is striking is that we move more often... and we know that that is a pretty good prediction of the future number of new infections." Since vehicle counts data is closely connected to people’s movements, it is worthwhile to investigate whether Steven Van Gucht’s statement is valid, i.e., how well traffic intensity correlates with Covid-19 infections.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/cover%20photo%20-%20blog%205_1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/cover%20photo%20-%20blog%205_1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Three new thematic ICON projects on AI.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/three-new-thematic-icon-projects" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three new thematic ICON projects on AI." /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/three_new_thematic_icon_projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/three-new-thematic-icon-projects"><![CDATA[<p>The EluciDATA Lab of Sirris successfully initiates three new thematic ICON projects on AI
With the Flemish Policy Plan on Artificial Intelligence, which started in 2019, Flanders invests 32 million euros annually in Artificial Intelligence (AI). As part of this plan, VLAIO launched a special call for thematic ICON projects on Artificial Intelligence (AI-ICON) with the aim to bridge the gap between research results in the field of artificial intelligence and its applications in Flemish industry.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>ICON projects (Interdisciplinary Cooperative Research) allows multidisciplinary research teams of scientists and industry partners to work together to develop innovative solutions that then find their way into the market offerings of the participating partners and beyond. For the special ICON call on AI, the EluciDATA Lab of Sirris, identified 3 topics with a high industrial added value in Flanders, in collaboration with 3 consortia of academic and industrial partners:</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="tracy---trace-analytics">TRACY - Trace Analytics</h3>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The aim is to investigate how to optimally use the log data generated by industrial assets and refine existing AI and machine learning techniques targeted at time series analysis. To this end, TRACY will research how to handle the complexities of log data, e.g., the heterogeneity of the industrial assets, the lack of standardisation amongst log data and the scalable interactive visualisation of the heterogeneous data. The research is validated on complex industrial use cases as optimising the performance of compressors and decreasing the service cost of electrophotographic machines. The consortium consists of Xeikon, CMC, Datylon, I-Care and Yazzoom, and the EluciDATA Lab as a research partner.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="conscious---contextual-anomaly-detection-for-complex-industrial-assets">CONSCIOUS - Contextual aNomaly deteCtIon for cOmplex indUstrial aSsets</h3>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The focus is on context-aware anomaly detection in industrial machines and processes. In these complex environments, anomaly detection remains a big challenge caused by the highly dynamic conditions in which these assets operate. The overall objective is to research effective solutions to achieve a more accurate, robust, timely and interpretable anomaly detection in complex, heterogenous data from industrial assets by accounting for confounding contextual factors. The results will be validated on multiple real-world use cases in different domains. In this project, the EluciDATA Lab will collaborate with Skyline Communications, Duracell Batteries, I-care, Yazzoom, KU Leuven and University of Antwerp.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="atwi---hybrid-multi-modal-methodology-for-automatic-tool-wear-inspection">ATWI - Hybrid, multi-modal methodology for Automatic Tool Wear Inspection</h3>
<p><br /></p>

<p>The project aims to accurately analyze and predict the tool wear in metal cutting processes. Both direct (vision-based) and non-direct (data-driven) methods will be combined to develop a hybrid approach that defines new methods to extract relevant data for tool wear prediction, identify the correlation between status of the tool-wear and underlying data, and construct an innovative integration of the multimodal information in production strategies. The multidisciplinary Sirris team with experts from the Precision Manufacturing team, the EluciDATA Lab and the Mechatronics team of Sirris will collaborate with Exmore, Goddeeris, Buysse, Melotte, Tisea and KU Leuven.
Despite the highly-competitive call, all three proposals were selected for funding. This will allow the EluciDATA Lab to further support the industry in tackling its real-world challenges related to AI through joint industrial research for innovative solutions.
<a href="https://www.vlaio.be/nl/nieuws/10-miljoen-euro-vlaio-innovatiesteun-voor-artificiele-intelligentie-en-cybersecurity" target="_blank" alt="Visit VLAIO website for more information" class="text-blue-600 underline">Visit VLAIO website for more information</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The EluciDATA Lab of Sirris successfully initiates three new thematic ICON projects on AI]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/vlaio-agentschap-innoveren-ondernemen.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/src/assets/vlaio-agentschap-innoveren-ondernemen.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>